Guide to the Horace Capron Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Horace Capron papers
1837-1884
MS 128
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2
(4 boxes)
Mainly correspondence between U.S. and Japanese officials dealing with the business of the Kaitakushi (of which General Capron was commissioner and adviser), a department of the Japanese Government in charge of the settlement of Hokkaido. Persons prominent in the collection include David Amomen, Thomas Antisell, Murray S. Day, Joseph Henry, Thornton A. Jenkins, Governor K. Kuroda, Benjamin S. Lyman, Henry S. Monroe, George M. Robeson, John R. Rogers, William Tecumseh Sherman, and James R. Wasson.
Capron, Horace, 1804-1885
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Albert S. Capron, 1950.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Horace Capron Papers consist of twenty inches of correspondence and business papers spanning the period 1837 to 1884, with the bulk of material falling in the years 1872-1874 and 1877-1880.
The correspondence consists largely of Capron's communications with the Japanese "Kaitukushi" or "Commissioner for opening up and developing" regarding the agricultural modernization of the island of Yesso, now Hokkaido. Other correspondence, between Capron and various assistants and Japense or American officials, also relates to the development of Yesso. The letters are catalogued by Capron's correspondents under their names and under his name in the manuscript catalog.
The business papers consist largely of receipts and orders for farm equipment, plants and livestock from the United States, and of telegrams confirming their shipment to Japan. There are also several memoranda concerning relations between Japanese and American officials, plus several contracts and leases.
The miscellaneous papers consist of two articles written by K. Kuroda, Governor of Yesso, for the Japanese Gazette: an article(?) by Benjamin Smith Lyman on the Japanese climate; a handwritten list of Japanese-name plants with their English and botanical equivalents; and miscellaneous notes, addresses, and newspaper clippings.
The Horace Capron Papers were given to Yale University Library by Albert S. Capron in 1950.
Biographical / Historical
Horace Capron: worked in cotton manufacturing, 1829-1834; in 1834 commissioned colonel of the 32nd Regiment of Maryland Militia; opened a cotton factory, 1836; active in progressive farming and agricultural societies; from 1852-1854 special agent over certain Indian tribes in Texas; served in the Civil War, attaining rank of Brigadier-general in the Illinois cavalry; in 1867 appointed U.S. Commissioner of Agriculture, remaining until 1871, when he was appointed by the Japanese government as commissioner and chief advisor to the Kaitakushi Department in the development and settlement of Hokkaido; returned to the U.S. in 1875.
Agriculture; Asia; Hokkaido (Japan); Japan -- Economic policy; Agriculturists; Public officers; Soldiers; Amomen, David; Antisell, Thomas, 1817-1893; Capron, Horace, 1804-1885; Day, Murray S.; Henry, Joseph, 1797-1878; Jenkins, Thornton A. (Thornton Alexander), 1811-1893; Kuroda, Kiyotaka, 1840-1900; Lyman, Benjamin Smith, 1835-1920; Monroe, Henry Smith; Robeson, George M. (George Maxwell), 1829-1897; Rogers, John Rankin, 1838-1901; Sherman, William T. (William Tecumseh), 1820-1891; Wasson, James R.
- Inventory
  - Correspondence, 1868 January 29 - 1873 December 28 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1874 January 9 - 1875 December 14 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1877 February 6 - 1883 June 18, undated (Box 3)
  - Letterbook, 1873 April 12 - 1874 June 13 (Box 3)
  - Business, 1837, 1869 January 17 - 1884 November 12, undated (Box 4)
  - Miscellany
    - List of Japanese-name plants with English and botanical equivalents plus growth information, undated (Box 4)
    - "Copy of article furnished by press by Governor Kuroda", 1874 March (Box 4)
    - "Governor Kuroda's proposed reply to certain strictures... not published by my advice", 1874 January (Box 4)
    - The Climate of Japan by Benjamin Smith Lyman, undated (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous materials re: gardening and agriculture, 1871 - 1872, undated (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous notes, addresses, and newspaper clippings, undated (Box 4)